I'd call
the public hearing
to order.
And
first off, I'd like like to welcome Anne Marie
to
the Commission and for joining us. And
the first section will be a public hearing.
And
any of the Commission members
are able to ask questions as we go through the topics during
the public hearing. Once we actually get to the regular meeting and start deliberation,
only those
commission members that
are actually seated, the five commission members, will be able to
deliberate on the different articles. So feel free to ask away as we're going through this. Most
of the articles that
we're talking about we've been working on for quite a while, so I know you're at a little bit of a disadvantage there.
But we'll try and explain
what they're about as we go through.
I'm looking to see
if we had anybody from the public join us tonight. And so far,
I don't see
anybody from the public there. So
I guess the exciting
questions
on lighting of the athletic fields, that was last
meeting we went through and that will
no interest tonight.
But
at this point,
Marina, if you can allow me to share my screen, I'll call up the
other
regulation changes and we'll work our way through those. And I think they'll be a little quicker than what we had in the past.
Okay.
Can everybody see the section five for the ARD?
Yes.
>> Okay, very good.
So
Eric asked for a couple of changes on behalf of the town, and I put in a couple of changes just to
make them consistent
with what
we've done a couple of changes in the past. But
I'm going to go through what's different
on section five here
now.
And so the first change,
we talked about
accessory apartments.
And I added the word subject to affordable housing restrictions
because
by right, we're going to have
accessory apartments
if they're deemed affordable.
And so I put that in the list here.
Going down to home occupations,
I specified as of right, those not requiring a special permit,
and referred you back to the home occupation section.
And then the change that
Eric is asking for
is really a change that's
provided to us by the state. They say everybody's
going to go do this.
And that's to have as of right
in the
residential areas
the ability to establish a family day care home
or a group child care home,
which is really
small daycare centers. So I think
if memory serves me correctly, a family daycare center is six kids
or fewer,
and that includes any
kids that
the daycare center operator has, then the group childcare center goes up to 12.
But the state told us to put
those changes in, and so
that's why those are here.
So, at this point,
I'll ask if there are any questions
on the changes to as of right in the ARD
area.
Okay.
The next section includes
what we had
for special permit uses.
And
I added the word
kennels down here. So I thought if anybody was going to put a kennel
in a residential area,
we would want that to come
before the Commission and have a public hearing associated with it to get input from the neighbors.
So I added
kennels. If you remember back when we
had the
discussion on Scott Beebe's kennel application,
we didn't hold a public hearing
because there's a couple of places where
it's not clear whether a public hearing was needed or not for Class A kennel.
We processed that application because he had a huge field that he was working in. But going forward,
said, I think anybody who is going to be a neighbor to a kennel might want to have a say on that. So I added the word kennel there.
The other thing we did is I left child care centers in here.
And again, when we put the definition
in the definition section, so a child care center for a special permit
is a child care center that has more than 12 kids.
So it's larger
child care center.
And we thought if we were going to be more than what the state was telling us, had to allow as of right,
that would be by special permit. And so I left that in there as opposed to eliminating it where
that would be the case where we'd only allow the small child care centers.
Then at the end here, I added
by special permit accessory apartments not subject to affordable housing restrictions
and also added home occupations requiring a special permit in reference back to the article on
those.
So those
are the changes
in Section
five. Any questions on
the special permit?
Things.
>> Chad, if you have an accessory apartment but you don't want it to fall under affordable housing, you would have to apply through
a special permit. Right? That's correct. Okay.
>> Yep.
And I don't know if that means everybody's going to be just doing the special permit or not, but at least we're
building
the regulations
to support affordable housing if we can properly incentivize people to go there. I don't know that we've got that incentive starting out, but our regulations will support it
if and when we get there.
Okay, I am going to move on to Section 7, which is the Lake District.
Similar to
what we did in Section 5 back
last January when we were talking about the
municipal buildings,
we put house of worships and cemeteries
is as of right categories.
I don't think anybody's going to be building a cemetery in the Lake District
As I'm
thinking about the House of Worship,
I'm trying to
recall.
I think we did change it.
No, we've got house of worship or cemeteries
special permit.
So
that would be a change. I would like to put the house of worship and a cemetery
into
the special
permit category, take it out of there. So that's a mistake on my part.
If
people feel strongly that it should be there,
we can leave it there.
It dawned on me that I think we're asking a couple of houses of worship to put in special permits for
some
properties that are being used as
churches and temples.
So
we should be consistent with that here. So I'll
take care of that unless somebody on the commission feels strongly that we should be
including that there.
I
put in the family daycare
home, group daycare home,
just like we did in section five.
That was based on,
again, the state told us that's what they wanted for residential areas.
I added just to be consistent
with Section five, and I think it was a good idea
that we list all the as of right things and all the special permit uses.
So I added home occupations not requiring special permits
and accessory apartments subject to affordable housing restrictions.
And also here,
I put C section
4.111
Charlie, which talks about
the minimum lot size in Lake District to have an
accessory apartment
is, I think, 2.75
acres. So
that restriction remains in effect even though it's not spelled out right here. If you go back and look in this section, that's what it tells you.
So
any question on the as of rate uses in the Lake District?
Okay, moving down to the special permit.
Added municipal land uses similar to what we did in Section five back in January.
I just didn't want to
do any more changes than was necessary to get that changed through back then. Added public parks, playgrounds, athletic fields, and beaches,
similar to what we did in Section five.
And added the home occupations requiring special permits
and accessory apartments not subject to affordable housing restrictions.
Again, I will add the houses of worship and cemeteries
in the special permit section.
So
any questions on the special permit?
Thanks.
Okay,
very good. I thought that was kind of straightforward.
Next, we're going to talk about Chapter 15 signs.
Again, these
are
changes that were requested
by the town.
The first was a
change to the definition
well, not the definition of a billboard, but
right this minute, billboards are
prohibited.
Towns ask that we allow billboards
where specifically authorized by the Board of Selectmen on town owned property.
I'm
not completely
sold on
this idea
yet.
My concern goes back to
what we saw during the pandemic with all the signs along the road that
Sometimes you like signs, sometimes you don't. I'm not sure that the Board of Selectmen
can specifically
choose to authorize
signs. I think when we went through the change that we did most recently,
if somebody wants to put up a sign and you're allowed to put up a sign for one thing,
you have to be able to put up a sign for anything. We are not allowed to regulate the content.
And so that caused me
a little bit of concern there.
In addition, I didn't understand exactly how the process was going to work as far as
when
somebody wants a sign, who's going to make the sign,
what's going to standard be, who decides
what kind of sign is appropriate for putting around the park.
If the Commission thinks that this is something that we should do,
and I'm going to be
relying
heavily on input from Scott and Ann because
you two are on the board of Selectman,
the
body that was asking for this change.
We might be able to do something that specifically
limits
the signs to the fence around the soccer field or something if that's where it was planned to go.
You know, I don't think we would want to put the regulation in effect that somebody could put a billboard sign up on the
town property on the corner of Lake Road and Route 6, for instance.
>> Just to clarify, Jed, the signs that we're talking about here were signs
down at the soccer field along defense
line,
where the selectmen
thought that it would be good to have, to be able to have the people that are involved with the, the usage of that field to be able to put their, their signs up.
They were told previously that there was no regulation for them to put their signs up. So we're trying to make it so that they could put their signs up on
field, on the field fence
during
the season.
>> Okay. And and we could we
could restrict the wording on that when we get to deliberation to, you know, further restrict it there.
Again, my concern is that if we're selling sign space,
there might be some folks putting up signs that we're not keen to have posted.
And I don't know that we could stop them from doing that. I don't know that we could stop the Board of Selectmen from
not authorizing them.
So we'll
deliberate that.
But that was my concern, and I wanted to make sure that was on the record
so that
when we vote
eventually on the record,
that concern can be taken into consideration.
The
other change that
the town was looking for in
we wanted to add
public interest signs that were erected
as approved by the Board of Selectmen.
A quantity right now, if you read our
regulations,
the quantity would be understood to be one.
You know, we talked about banners over at the school where there's a significantly
larger quantity. I think that's the right answer. I think
the Board of Selectmen can
do that
within their purview and not be in any freedom of speech issues or whatever.
That's that.
The height,
again, my sense is that the banners over
at the school are at an appropriate height.
And right now, that's higher than 12 feet, which I
think our regulation limits it to either 10 feet or 12 feet, something like that.
The town was also asking to increase the size
from 16 square feet to 32 square feet.
I think that's reasonable. There was some
concern that the
sign that we
had approved for putting on the senior center
was a little too small at 16 square feet.
I don't know that it needs to be 32 square feet, but that gives
the Board of Selectmen the latitude to go up to that
make that call.
We got a little feedback from
our attorney
on,
I think, the original words in here
with
the concurrence or something of the Board of Education, we weren't going to put any signs at the elementary school
without the concurrence of the Board of Education.
And Attorney Branch's
concern there was
we were advocating our responsibility
as a zoning commission
to another entity, and we shouldn't do that.
Certainly, we would be working
closely with the Board of Education.
We're not going to put signs up over there that they don't want.
But we changed it to prior notification of the Board of Education or their designee, which could be the principal if they so choose.
>> Hey, Jed. Yes, Steve. Question. On this section,
it says the town of Andover
may elect public interest signs,
you know, up to 32 square feet. So
wouldn't that cover what they need at the soccer fields?
Each individual So sign could be four by
>> I don't think an advertising sign
is a public interest sign. All right. Fair enough.
And so
it is covered that way.
And again, the definition of a billboard
talks about
any time you're advertising
something
off the premises
of the thing,
like advertising Andover Pizza at the soccer field,
it calls that a billboard. And right now, billboards are prohibited.
Got it. Okay. So they're putting that change in there to
get around
that.
Thank you.
>> Any other questions on
the sign
thing here?
Okay,
we
talked about
the parking modifications
last time.
The last thing on the list is definitions.
Architectural
plans,
that
was a
definition that I'm pretty sure I got from Attorney Branch.
I
had a definition of architectural plans.
And he said, no, those are really floor plans. Architectural plans are more detailed. And so we changed in
the section on accessory apartments
to require floor plans.
And I think that has the detail that we're looking for
in that.
So
architectural
plans are
discussed a couple of other places,
and we have the more detailed
requirements for that. Floor plans is what we were looking for for the accessory apartments.
Child care center
each of the definitions here on child care center, family day care home, group day care home
are
essentially
exactly the same. And so one of my concerns was
they didn't
tell us what we needed to know.
The limit of six, the limit of 12, or greater than 12.
Attorney Branch's concern was that
if we put specific numbers in there and we don't reference back to the Connecticut general statute
and they change the general statute, then our
definitions
are
out of whack with the
Connecticut general statutes.
I could live with that because I thought that in that rare occasion that we might get a application
for a child care center of some description there,
we could ask Jim to look it up and he would tell us what
the numbers are now.
Or I could look it up. Any of us could look it up. So I went with what our attorney recommended
with respect to those.
The last definition
is
lot frontage. We've been trying to get this in our definition sections for a while.
It's
very slightly different from what we had talked about months ago
when
Eric Jim and I and Mark Branch got together to go through the changes to make sure that I understood what we were talking about before we had the public hearing.
We tweaked down the words just a little bit here.
The
distance along a public street that either exists concurrently as proposed as part of subdivision, that's the same as before.
We tweaked down the words frontage may include distance along the street on sides of the lot that are adjacent to each other.
And
we don't
that's a minor change from
what we had before, but we thought that
ended up being a little bit clearer.
So anyhow,
>> yes, you have I have a concern about
that definition.
Okay. It
doesn't speak to
the fact that it has to be a straight line or contiguous.
I mean, peep people make horseshoe lots
or have.
Yep.
And
they they could use the frontage on on both sides,
two
different lengths of frontage.
And quite frankly, the regulations just aren't set up to accommodate that elsewhere.
>> Thought that the second sentence
included
that,
you know, and
again, I'm not
>> Yeah. Well, I'd like to talk about that also, Jed. Go ahead, Scott. Yep. I'm not sure that I understand
even what that says. Say, what if it's on a corner and it's,
the
a street and B Street,
if there's a 100 feet on either street, then it's
>> That is what regulation? Yep. That's what that says.
That's what that's intended to mean.
What I didn't want to have happened, if there was a lot with a, and I think the term is through lot,
but a lot that has a street on the front boundary and a street on the back boundary and 100 feet on each, I didn't want to call that 200 feet of frontage, but if a guy had a corner lot, I thought that 200 feet of frontage, if it was a 100 to a 100 would be okay.
>> Maybe you could say, I. E,
two different streets or some clarify it in some way.
I didn't know what that meant while we talked It about
>> isn't clear to me either, quite honestly. I'm
sure I read it before.
Didn't mention it, but now that I'm looking at it,
it's not clear.
>> Okay.
Well, we'll hold that thought till we deliberate on it. You understand what we're trying to do. Yep. And
And if we need to make those words clear, we can certainly do that.
Somebody
mentioned,
I can't tell if it's a straight line
or what.
And I intentionally
went with distance along the public street.
And if you remember back
on the Pine Ridge
subdivision that we did,
Those guys did not have
50 foot straight line across. But
if we measured the distance along the street, they had the 50 feet.
And so
we did that there, and I wanted to make our definition consistent with what we did there.
That's what they used for their frontage?
>> They did. They used distance along the street.
And we had talked about that at the time
and thought that was a reasonable approach
to take.
So, any other questions on the lot frontage definition?
That definition has been three years in the making.
Has been. We can get it over the finish line this time.
And
certainly, I'm not married to any of the words.
If there's a better way to say it, or if we don't want to include the adjacent
the corner lot scenario,
I could put in such as is seen in the corner lot or something.
But hopefully
everybody understands what it is that the words are trying to say here.
If we want to change the words, we can. If we want to make them
you know, clearer,
we can do that.
>> Well, that sentence that sentence could be,
if if you add what you just said as in
a corner lot, so clarify exactly what you're saying, because you're, you're, you're talking
about something very specific there. So as in a corner lot, but then if you have, which front had gone two roads, you know, one's the front and one's the back, I don't think that
that's
right frontage.
>> Okay.
Yes. I think that's why you said adjacent, right? Yes.
>> That's the reason for adjacent.
And I can put, I'll just, I can add the words in there
as in a corner lot.
>> I have a question about that, too.
I'm
not muted.
We had that situation on Hendee where
you said there wasn't enough frontage
because there was a town owned drip of land there. Now
that's not considered public street because it's the town owned land. Is that
>> That is correct. That's correct. Yeah, that is correct. They did not have frontage
because
the town owned
the frontage. The town had frontage,
the property owner did not in that particular case.
Now, he could have gone back and tried to buy that piece of property
or he had frontage on the other side of the house,
but he didn't want to consider it that way. He wanted to break off that lot
to
the one side of the house that he didn't have frontage on.
And so, we could not allow in that particular case
taking a lot that met the regulations
and transforming it into a lot that didn't meet the regulations.
>> I I still have a problem with the town owned that strip. It seems like the town owns the street, so the town owns the land and it seems like the same thing.
They had the frontage along that town
owned strip of land, it would be the same as the street. Yep,
>> I
understand.
But they also had adequate frontage the way the lot was currently configured,
and they wanted to change it. So, you know, I don't want to go That
was not the easiest
decision that we had to work our way through. And that's why I was trying to come up with a definition
of frontage to put in here because we didn't have one then. And
>> That messes why we have this right now. Yep. Mhmm. So.
>> Okay.
I
think
from a public hearing perspective,
that concludes
all the changes that we were looking to make.
Did we cover the lighting?
>> We did cover the lighting. We did that last meeting.
Oh, okay, last meeting. Yep, and
>> we will be able to deliberate that. We covered that extensively last time. I do expect there to be quite a bit of discussion
as we
work our way through that
this time. But Okay.
Yep.
So, I think we're done. Eric, have we satisfied
your desire to
cover all the things that we were talking about changing?
>> So from my perspective,
yes, I don't have any more commentary
other than,
the town,
I think,
would be willing to drop
the changes
to section four
as they relate to lighting
and
only go with the
our request
our lighting requests,
specific
to lighting if that makes sense.
>> Okay, yep. So and again, here's the section four.
And these were all the things
that were all the things that you talked about
low levels of lighting on the adjacent properties and dark sky compliant
and not being able to see the actual light and that sort of thing.
And
I think that
I appreciate
the town
wanting to pull that request.
Then we won't talk about that one anymore. We'll just talk we'll spend our time on the other.
Any other information that
anybody
has
or wants to make sure are included in the public record
before we close the public hearing?
What
exactly,
Eric, are you
pulling?
>> The request for the modification that's in yellow. Yeah, this here, this line.
Oh, okay.
>> So what that would require
the
town do if they want to put lighting there
is they would have to
dark sky
compatible,
make sure that
it's a shielded light source not seen from the adjacent properties and not a hazard to the drivers.
And lighting at the property line shall not exceed 0.2 lumens per square foot.
Those
things were
that the town was asking exemption for.
And
I think
Eric's concluded that they would be able to comply with those requirements.
Very good.
>> Okay.
So
if there are no further
questions or comments,
I will close the public hearing at 07:30
Deb,
can you hear me? Yes. Is that Leanne?
Yes. Okay. Yep.
>> I
I tried once again to sign in to the meeting
on time with the agenda posted that I see on the town website, and it was the incorrect one.
When did you get that information? Today? This evening?
Yes.
>> Okay.
I mean, I came in through the calendar.
Yeah.
And it was fine.
And it should be the same
instructions are on the agenda.
>> No. I I think, Ann Marie's right. I tried it through the agenda also, but then I noticed that there was a supplemental email
that had the correct information.
So I use that.
>> But the supplemental email said that was gonna be corrected on the website on the town website, which I would assume would include
the agenda itself,
which is how I went in, not through the calendar.
>> I was told I mean, I had asked for that that change to be made, and I I was led to believe it had been. I I did not
check the agenda. I
did verify that the calendar worked.
>> Yeah.
I've got the agenda here. It's got the correct one.
Printed this tonight.
>> You print that off from
the website,
or did you print that off from the email that got sent out with an updated agenda? I got printed from the email. Yeah. Okay. That's why it's correct. Yes.
Leanne is
undoubtedly correct in her statement that
on the website, if you go to the agenda,
it still has the wrong information.
And when I said we were
somebody had commented how smoothly we getting on tonight. I said it wasn't because we weren't working on it yesterday
to try and make it that way. And that was one that slipped through the cracks. Apologize, Leanne.
We got it fixed a
couple of different ways, but the way you tried was not fixed.
>> Okay. Well, again, it specifically
says it's going to appear on the town website. It doesn't direct
anyone to the agenda
or
the calendar or one but not the other.
So if this happens again next month I'll have to try even earlier and try to remember to go into the calendar
in case this happens for the third month in a row.
Since I wasn't on the beginning of the meeting, can you tell me quickly what was done about accessory apartments?
>> We did not discuss accessory apartments today. We covered that last month in the public hearing,
and we will cover it again in deliberation
when we go through it. So we did not discuss the accessory apartments tonight.
Okay,
fine.
>> Okay.
So,
going back,
I closed the public hearing. I think if I recall, it was 07:34.
Is that correct, Marina?
And Marina, you're muted.
We've got it on the tape what time I closed it. I'll open the regular meeting at 07:38.
I'll call the regular planning and zoning meeting to order.
First up on the agenda is
roll call and seating of alternates.
I see that the
entire commission is present, Anne Cremay, Scott Prasan,
Leigh Ann Hutchinson, Steve Nelson, and myself. So Susan
and Anne Marie, you will not be seated as alternates tonight.
Additions or changes to the agenda?
I have none. Does anybody have any additions
or changes that
they would like to propose?
Okay.
Hearing none, we'll move on.
Any public comment?
And
I hope that
there's not a lot of folks that found themselves in a situation similar to Leanne.
I do know that the public that attended the last meeting all got on through the calendar.
And so when they wanted to make it there, they did. So
moving on to
new business, there is none. We'll go to old business,
discussing
the application of the town of Andover for various text amendments.
I do plan to go just a little bit out of order here.
I want to get to section five and section seven first
because
those are
sections that Eric's got a commitment
to the state to answer
about our regulations supporting what they've asked to do.
I will go back to
Section
five
And
I will make a motion to approve Section five
as it is shown
here.
Second.
>> Thank you, Steve.
Any discussion
on that particular
section of our regulations?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote. Anne?
Aye.
Scott?
Aye. LeeAnne?
Leanne, you're on mute, I think.
Oh, yes. Sorry. Yes, aye.
>> Steve?
Aye.
And I vote aye as well.
The motion to amend section five passes
five-zero-zero.
Moving
on to Section seven,
I will make a motion to approve
these regulations
as presented
with the exception of moving the houses of worship
in cemeteries
from a permitted use
to a special permit
use.
Second.
>> Thank you, Steve. Any discussion?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote. Anne?
Aye.
Scott? Aye.
Leigh Ann?
Aye.
Steve?
>> And I vote aye as well. The proposed changes to Section seven
is amended by moving the House of Worship and Cemetery Special Permit
are approved.
Okay, next up is
Chapter 15, Signs.
I will make a motion to approve the changes
as
shown.
Second doesn't mean we won't have discussion on it after we have the motion to approve it.
So I'm looking for a second. I second that, Jim. Okay. Thanks, Scott.
Any discussion on
the changes
as
listed here?
>> The
billboard section, I thought we were going to
look at alternatives to that for the Board of Selectmen.
>> Well,
I didn't want to look at that in the public hearing part. I wanted do that in the deliberation section. I
expressed my concern about it in the public hearing
part, just to be on the record there.
I've kind of
said what I think. I'm
interested in what the Commission thinks,
especially Anne and Scott, who
are on the Board of Selectmen as well.
What do we think about
putting up signs,
billboard signs along the fence at the soccer field? Is that something that we think we should be doing?
Is that something
that we don't think we should be doing?
And if we do think we should be doing it, should we put more restrictions
in place that would limit it specifically to the soccer field?
>> I tend to think we need to limit it to the
fence on the soccer field.
I mean, I'm okay with that because that's a pretty common thing to have signs along the edge of a field or a hockey rink or that kind of thing. So
I'm fine with the sign that is that we need to specify that it's there,
not just town owned property. Would
>> we be happy with political signs going up at the soccer field?
No.
>> And
do we think that
we can prevent
political signs from going up at the soccer field?
>> Jed, I thought that was expressly prohibited,
political signage on
municipal property.
>> That certainly can't be true because
that's where all the signs end up being.
If you if you go
if you go to the transfer station
>> Yeah. They're there. No no doubt about it. Yep. I
>> thought at the transfer station, people were out on the road, though.
>> Well, that's town property too. And That's fair.
It
I'm I'm
trying to look in my
>> I'm not suggesting it's in our regulations. I thought it was elsewhere
statutes
such.
>> Political
signs fall under the definition of billboard signs or billboard signs Well,
>> so
it does under political position signs, it says no political position signs should be allowed on publicly owned property.
So that was a quick call on that.
I don't know that we
often comply with that one very well
because we put them up at the town hall,
put them up at the transfer station.
>> I remember years ago, was an issue when when the
fire department
used their signage,
their signboard for political
for an election.
Yep. And they
moved the sign across the street is what they did.
>> I don't know. I'm just not sold on
the
benefit.
I think it was Scott or Anne who talked about Scott, I think it was you that was talking about
we wanted to allow the teams that play there the ability to put up their signs.
Right.
Yeah.
>> So,
were we not looking to advertise for places like Andover Pizza and stuff like that to
put up a sign there?
>> I
would say that
in addition to the team signs,
that
type of signage would
we were also looking
to have up there.
>> So we were looking for advertising signs.
Well,
you know There's
>> a way to generate revenue. It's expensive to operate that field down there.
>> I think it's fine to put the signs there. I just think we should specify in the wording that it's for the,
you know, the the town fields,
the athletic
fields.
Yeah.
>> And we're expecting
what what kind of revenue,
you know, do we expect to
to get from putting up signs for a season? We
gotten that far yet, Jed.
Yep.
>> I mean, if you go to Tolland, all the athletic fields in Tolland have the same type of signage
or advertising.
>> You know, it's Everywhere you go, they're Yeah. Fields are covered. Yeah.
Signage. I don't see a problem with it.
>> Okay.
So if we said signs except when specifically authorized by the board of selectmen
on the fence around the soccer field.
>> Yeah, but does it even have to be specified by the Board of Selectmen? Can we just say billboard signs are permitted
along the fence at the
athletic fields?
>> Billboard signs are by definition greater than 32 square feet. Oh, greater?
There's
two caveats to what a billboard sign is.
It advertises
a facility
off its property
and it's greater than
32 square feet.
>> Can we can we just say
limited to 32 square feet per sign?
Because that gives them a four by eight.
That's a sheet of plywood. You can get plenty of advertising on that along the fence.
>> So let me just read the definition.
I looked it up here.
Billboard, a sign which directs attention to a business, commodity, service,
or entertainment conducted,
sold, or offered elsewhere than upon the premises where such sign is located
or to which it is affixed,
or any sign
having a sign face in excess of 32 square feet. So it's an or. It's in either of those things. It doesn't have to be both.
And a banner is how many square feet, Jed?
Banner is not
I don't think there's
>> We don't define banner. We don't address banner. Yeah, we don't address the size.
>> It's
been limited by
the sign
size requirement
for the given
usage.
So,
home occupation signs are, I think, four square feet.
A common sign is 16 square feet. We allow in a couple of cases up to 32 square feet.
And in this case, below
here,
we're authorizing the Board of Selectment to go up to 32 square feet. So
they could certainly
and again, advertising
is
not a public interest sign, but we could change the wording up here
to require it to be authorized by the Board of Selectmen
on the fence at the soccer field not to exceed 32 square feet. That sounds good. Yeah, I'd be good with that. Let me write that down before I forget it.
Okay, so again, I'm going to change
change for billboards to say signs except when specifically authorized by the Board of Selectmen
on the fence at the soccer field
and no more than 32 square feet.
>> Do we even have to say authorized by the Board of Selectmen?
>> Could be the Board of Selectmen or her representative.
What No, I'm just saying want to make sure. Billboard
>> signs
are permitted
along the fence at the soccer field
if they're limited to 32 square feet.
>> This gets into the issue of I don't know how the process is going to work yet. We haven't kind of gone through that.
But I would think
the Board of Selectmen,
maybe they're going to Eric, do you have a sense on how this might work if it were approved?
>> I I
don't really understand. The Board of Selectmen
hadn't really fleshed it out. They clearly were interested
in
being able to sell space along the fence
for advertising
to support the maintenance
costs of the field.
But I don't believe they'd really fleshed it out completely
because I told them under the current zoning regulations, it was illegal anyway, and they couldn't do it.
So their ask to me was to ask the commission to change that, which I've done so. So Okay. So the 32 square feet should be plenty.
>> Yep.
My sense is it's okay to leave as authorized by the board of selectmen or we could even put
or his representative,
which is going to be Eric.
But if somebody wants to put up a sign there,
I don't want them just going out and hanging up a sign. There's got to be a way for the town to get
the funding for it. And so
the Board of Selectmen is not going to authorize that sign to go up unless they paid their fee. That's
a pretty go or no go kind of thing.
But
it's got to be authorized by
somebody,
and
we could put the word
Board of Selectmen
or their designated representative,
which is going to put it down most likely, at least to start, is going to go to Eric.
May have
that go to,
you know, his admin assistant or something like that.
But it's whoever they designate, that gives them a vehicle for the Board of Selectmen not approving it, but we've got the process to get the funding coming into the town.
Maybe it needs to go to a
finance person or the tax collector or something, I don't know. But if we put
her there designated
representative,
that would allow
that process to work.
>> Yeah. I I agree with that. And and add what you said before, Jed, about the not to exceed
32 square feet. Yep.
Okay. So did you already make the motion on signs yet?
>> I did, and we're discussing it now. We've made
a motion.
We've
seconded the motion.
Now we are discussing the motion.
>> Chairman Larson,
I'm
looking for some clarification.
Is the commission interested in
having the content of these signs monitored?
That's what I heard before,
meaning approved.
I mean, I know that,
I mean, this is town property. They have
the town has the ability
to say what goes up and what doesn't.
Now it's unlike a, you know, a private property where freedom
of speech issues arise,
I believe.
John, are you on line here?
>> Yeah, I am.
I
think that the
zoning regulations should not be in the business of regulating
zoning or signage content.
But obviously if this is exclusively for town property,
these would be,
you know,
leased and approved by the town. So, you know, you could put that authority
to, you know, approve or deny any particular sign on the Board of Selectmen or the Board of Education or whomever.
But I
don't think
the regulation should be in the business of regulating content.
>> The Board of Selectmen should be not in the business of regulating content.
Correct.
Thank you, John.
>> Well, we do have the regulation in there that says no political signs
on town property.
So that
eliminates
a whole host of things.
I'm might be a question,
if
somebody wants to put up their sign
advertising
beer, wine,
liquor,
cannabis,
is that what we want out there?
And I think with the regulation
as specified,
we would have to allow that.
>> Well, couldn't the Board of Selectmen? Because it says when specifically authorized Board
of Selectmen, couldn't they regulate that?
They can try.
They might get sued.
Yeah.
>> But if we didn't like the way that the signage was working out, we could always change the regulation back to what it is now,
and that would be
the end of that experiment.
So I'm okay with letting it go and seeing if
I don't like the result
if the Commission doesn't like the result, we can ultimately change it again. And
we
didn't have the controls in there that we thought were appropriate.
Maybe
that won't
come to pass. I don't know. I
don't know that we should be advertising cannabis or
alcohol down there.
But I don't know that would withstand the legal challenge if somebody were to
want to put that there.
Might not ever become an issue. I don't know. But that
was my concern from First Amendment
concern when I was talking about, do the Board of Selectmen,
can they specifically
authorize
or
specifically not authorize
content?
And I don't think they can.
>> Think, Jen, if I might. Yep, go ahead, John. I think, again, these are two sort of separate issues, the
the zoning regulation
relative to content.
I think that we probably, I don't know if the political
prohibition, the political sign prohibition
is just
within
that 75
foot perimeter of polling areas or on any town property?
Well,
>> it's clearly in our regulations,
it says no political position
>> signs on town's property. Yeah. I mean, that could be a larger discussion we don't need to get into tonight. But, you know, if someone put up a sign that said, you know,
Johnny Walker for president,
you know, is that political?
It's, you know, satirical.
You know, you kind of get into these, like,
numerous gray areas. Yep.
But,
yeah, and why to a certain extent, content, the Supreme Court has sort of,
you know, put, you know, it's a cold
water on, you
know, zoning regulations ability to regulate content. But as far as,
you know, if someone is leasing space essentially from the town to put up a sign
that the town in, through its board of selectmen could have a policy about what sorts of signs are allowed or not,
you know, sort of independent of the zoning
thing, because this is, it's a business transaction. It's not a first amendment thing really.
>> Okay.
Yep. I hear all that,
and
I
don't know the answer to that one. Now,
can pass on
voting on
signs tonight
until we do some more research, but I'm not sure
that more research is going to get us anything. You know, there's nothing
harder in the zoning reg world
than signs.
And if you've attended the Connecticut Bar Association
training for
land use stuff,
they have a section on
ridiculous
sign
challenges
in how they come out and all that kind of stuff. And there's
no winners. Once you allow a sign,
pretty much anything goes is
what I see.
And I was concerned about how we would regulate that. And my thought was, at this point in time,
I wasn't ready to go there. But
that's
a call for
the commission to make,
and
we can see how it goes.
It's pretty specific.
Yeah.
>> It is. I don't know that it's constitutional,
but it's very specific.
Well, anyhow.
>> Ted, can you read back the wording as you have it now for that? Yep.
>> I got
billboard signs except where specifically authorized by the Board of Selectmen or their designated representative
on the fence at the soccer field
in no more than 32 square feet.
Sounds good to me. Okay.
>> We'll
go with that.
There was one other
aspect
of
the change for the public interest signs that
I wanted to discuss
and that was the issue of
does Jim as the zoning agent
know what the Board of Selectmen have approved
with
respect to a public interest sign.
Let's say the Board of Selectmen
were to approve
putting up the banners at Andover Elementary School.
We did get a letter from Eric
saying that the Board of Selectmen approved hanging
the banners there.
And I guess going forward,
it would be nice to
have a little more granularity on that. And I don't know that we need to put it in the regulation.
We can get it from Eric that how many signs,
how big are the signs, how high are the signs,
and that sort of thing. And that would have to almost come in as a request.
I
was considering how to make
the process work with a
signed
application.
And that got too hard. The Board of Selectmen can do what they want. But in the case of the school, the school had to go to the Board of Selectmen and say, this is what we'd like to do. And then the Board of Selectmen approves it. But there ought to be enough detail in there that we put that in the record and we can tell that
the person who is
hanging the sign
actually did what was approved.
And I think
Eric would probably be willing to
give us that.
I just didn't know if we needed to put some specific words in here that would require it.
Or
the commission
members think that we should put those words in there?
>> Well, it would be in the meeting minutes, wouldn't it?
>> It might be.
I'm thinking back to the
banners at the school,
and
none of that detail was provided
in the minutes.
None of that detail was provided
to anybody, I think. We all knew what was going to happen,
but we didn't know how high it was going to go.
And we didn't know
well, we knew the size.
Saw the banner. We didn't know how high it was going to go.
If somebody wants to do something like that, I think they ought to
have it spelled out. The sign at the senior center, it would be part of the
plan that would be approved
when we approve
the senior center.
So, now we can make a change to that, and we'll be talking about a change to a site plan later on tonight when we talk about the propane tank.
But better not specify what it is that
we want to do so that the zoning enforcement officer
can enforce it
if he chooses.
Yeah. And I'm willing to work with Eric, if Eric's willing to work with us,
to figure that out. I know the two cases where
we put up public interest signs, one's at the elementary school, one's over at the
public works with the snowplow out there,
we got a letter from Eric saying that it was approved.
I just think it should have a little bit more detail to it.
Okay, so I'll work with Eric and we'll do that. If it doesn't work, we can add
more definition to the
requirements,
but
we'll figure out what we want and work to do that.
So,
I make a motion to amend
the proposed
changes to Chapter
15 signs.
As we discussed changing the
billboard
to say billboards
of signs except when specifically
authorized by the Board of Selectmen
or their designated representative
on the fence.
I will add the word,
the Andover Veterans Memorial Park soccer field Soccer field, yeah. At no more than 32 square feet.
Second.
>> Okay, thanks, Steve.
So, at this point, I think any other discussion on anything with the signs?
Hearing
none, I will call for a vote on the amendment.
And then after that, we will call for a vote on the change to Chapter 15. So first up is
to approve the amendment, Anne?
Aye.
>> Scott? Aye.
Leigh Ann?
Aye.
Steve?
Aye. Can I vote aye as well? The amendment passes
five-zero-zero. And
now
back to the vote on the
change to Section 15
as amended.
I will call for a vote on that. Anne?
Aye. Scott? Aye.
Lee Ann?
Aye.
>> Steve? Aye. And I vote aye as well.
The changes
as amended
to Chapter 15 signs are approved. Thank you, everybody.
Okay, I guess
I'm going to stop sharing
this.
Okay, we're
going to deliberate
on Section 4.11,
the accessory apartments.
And
this is
what we discussed
last time.
Somewhere in here where
there's the inconsistency,
deed restricted for ten years
and up here, deed restricted for forty years.
So, we need to make it consistent there one way or the other.
And I
took out architectural plans
and put floor plans.
And that
is it.
Now,
We'll start I will make a motion to approve the changes to Section 4.11
accessory apartments.
Second.
>> Thank you, Steve.
Any discussion
on
the regulations
as
specified here? And I guess I will start out by saying
my recommendation is that we go consistently
with
forty years.
That's based on the recommendation of attorney branch.
If somebody doesn't want forty years,
they've got the
ability to go for a special permit where they don't have to do affordable housing at all.
I would hope that somewhere down the road we have a housing committee or some group that's working on affordable housing that we put into
place a process that makes this
easy to
be more conducive to go the affordable housing route. It's not there yet.
But that doesn't mean that our
regulations
shouldn't go
to to where we want to go, not necessarily where we are today.
Any other discussion on
the affordable housing
thing?
>> I have a question. Yeah, go ahead, Anne. I
know that a lot of this is based on the state statute or state recommendation.
Did they have a number of years in theirs? Was it ten? Was it forty? Was it twenty?
Did they say anything?
>> What they said is
for an accessory department,
it only needed to be
deed restricted for ten years.
That's why when I initially wrote up the change,
I put ten years there. And Mark said, I really think you should go at forty years.
Why? I was concerned, well, because at the end of ten years,
the affordable
accessory apartment
no longer counts as an affordable apartment.
And we have made so little progress
on the state goal of increasing our
affordable housing that counts
that he thought we needed to do something
that might head us that direction.
We did talk about the concern that if we make it so hard with no incentive,
that nobody's going to go that way and they're all going to go special permit.
I don't think the Commission will be bogged down
by
special permits for
accessory
apartments.
We're seeing maybe one a year. And so
my suspicion is
that every
application will come in wanting to go the special permit route
because there's no reason not to.
I'm Okay with that.
And if at some point we come up with something that
will incentivize
going with the deed restriction so that we get serious about solving the affordable housing thing,
then we can do that too. My real desire is to have more affordable housing. Whether it counts or not, it would be nice if it counted.
But
we need to have
things that people can afford to live in. And so I'm okay with making that forty years. And I understand that maybe
a lot of people
will choose the route of going to a public hearing because it's not all that much more difficult than
just putting in an application when you get right down to it.
>> When
we
say forty year restriction, does that mean that the
amount that
the owner gets for that apartment can't go up for forty years or does it have to just stay within the
30%,
which could be going
up. The dollar amount could be going up because their income goes up. Well, and I think the number is 80% of the median income.
>> There's also a desire that somebody not spend more than 30% of their income on housing.
But the number is 80%
of
median income. With median income,
I can't remember if it's $100,000 or $120,000
somewhere in that ballpark.
So we're talking about
$80,000 to $90,000
max for an accessory apartment.
Think that's all you're going get anyhow. Plus the income then. Yeah.
Jed, if Yeah, go I might
>> ahead, John. You can take 30% of that. Right. And it's a number that gets determined by HUD each year.
And so it does increase with inflation and with, as income go up. And so there's basically an annual reporting requirement
of the property owner to
the town to verify what the income limits are, what the rental limits are, and that their tenant qualifies under that level.
>> Yeah. And I guess it would be fair to say starting out
that if somebody did want to have a deed restricted
accessory apartment,
it's probably going to go to
John
no, not John,
Jim Jim.
To set up in
the land use office down there
a little
tracking system, kind of like we're trying to track
home occupations
and that sort of thing.
And again, I think it's going to be years before we see anything that would be any kind of significant burden. And I think that
Lynn
in the land use office
with little oversight by Jim would be able to handle that very easily at the park we are.
Nothing would make me happier than if we had to go to the Board of Selectmen and say we need to hire more staff because we've got 150
accessory
apartments to
manage for affordable housing,
then we would never be under the gun for affordable housing again. I don't think we're going get there anytime soon.
>> Just for the record, I want to make it clear that the income
requirements apply for initial occupancy.
This
regulation doesn't
make you
evict somebody because they're over income.
But it's still
counted as an affordable unit.
It's still a deed restricted unit.
But I just wanted to make that clear. Okay.
>> That Yeah. Thank you. Yeah, I guess somebody's income could go up
faster.
Again, the reason I wanted to have the exemption
to go special permit is
if you had family members where your parents,
you know, they had
a significant income, and now we'd be saying you couldn't go into an accessory apartment. I don't think that's right. But right this minute, I think that will get used more often than not. But we'd have to see.
Have a Go few other
ahead, Leigh Ann.
>> Yes, if you're done. I think this was part of what I missed trying to sign into last month's meeting.
So you covered one of the things I was going to ask because it's it's I'm I'm looking at last month's minutes. It says deed restrictions ten years versus four years, which you just covered.
I had a couple of questions.
One is, were there any new points brought out that aren't listed in the minutes?
And I can read that for everybody who doesn't have it pulled up.
Any just
taking things, for example, to do with
size or
detached versus attached
or anything like that. We've covered that in the past. Was any of that brought up last month
for change,
or is it limited to these things that are listed here, which which does say you discussed rental charges, deed restrictions
dash are there different lengths of time options available affording full housing points,
and how to incentivize
affordable housing?
>> Those
were the only changes to what we had previously talked about. Again, the key points there are we aligned the size restrictions for the accessory apartments with what the state recommended.
And then we also
had a requirement in here.
We made it a requirement,
and
this goes into some discussion with
various
other towns that have worked their way through. We have said that the owner shall reside
in either the principal dwelling or the apartment.
Didn't
want
that to be a rental thing where you're renting out both things, which essentially makes it a duplex.
And then we changed architectural
plans to floor plans and put both the definition for floor plans and architectural
plans in our definition section.
>> So, okay. So I remember the part about the owner occupied and one or the other
aspects.
Can
you refresh my memory? What if people want to make
an appeal?
Maybe appeal isn't it it's not an actual appeal, but but I guess it would be an appeal for
a change in size
or
but the other thing you mentioned about,
architectural
definitions and things like that,
are they free to come to the commission and make points about that? Do they have to go to ZBA, or would they start with us and explain why they wanted some sort of variation
if they wanted something like that?
>> I
think, you know, they
can certainly come to us when they're making their
bid for a site plan, but
we would not have the authority to allow
exception to the regulations that we draft.
That would have to go to the Zoning Board of Appeals.
And
again, I think
we're
allowing an accessory apartment up to 1,000 square feet now. That's an increase
of a couple 100 square feet over what our current
regulation allows. And
I don't think we want
too much bigger than that. I can't imagine somebody
coming up with a hardship to go before zoning board of appeals
on why they need something greater than 1,000 square feet or something.
So,
yeah, I think, you know, what
we put is what you get.
If you can't live with that,
maybe you're not really in the market for an accessory apartment.
Maybe you're looking for a subdivision or something. I don't know.
>> Okay, well, think you answered my question, and I'm not thinking of anything else to compare it to specifically.
It's just in some of our regulations
about any given thing,
sometimes there are
sometimes there isn't, sometimes there isn't room for,
you know, some I don't know what a good word is, but, you know, just some leeway. Yep. So I was just asking again because I think I missed part of this discussion last month.
But I think you answered my question about what people would do,
because you had mentioned taking a lot of it from the state regulations, what people would do if they had
a a reason they could demonstrate
if they did want a
variation from it. And I'm not using variation in the sense of a variance, just a variation,
anything they might come up with. So
but I think you've answered that as far as it probably wouldn't happen unless they went to ZBA. Yep. Now,
>> one other thing that we had talked about one time, and I saw this happen
on a lot over in Columbia.
There was a small house
on
a piece of property,
and they turned that small house
into a carriage house
and essentially made it the accessory apartment
by building a 3,000 square foot house next to it. So it
still met the 33%
floor
area, but no
larger than the house. So you could do that if you wanted. You could build a big house to make the little house the accessory apartment as long as it met our requirements here. Nothing prohibits you from doing that.
We're trying Okay, and I guess
>> yep. No, we're trying to make things that are affordable. When you start to get these huge things that
are not any longer affordable at that point.
>> Right. That makes sense. I
guess I was just thinking, again, without any specifics, was just thinking, since we are trying to encourage the
affordable housing,
and this is one aspect of it, you know, without and and we may not get many, if any, of these inquiries
at all. I guess I was just thinking of,
you know, because every property is different,
that we may get some people looking for some sort of variation on this. And I was wondering if we've had any more discussion last month, but I think you've answered my question.
>> Okay.
Any other Thank you. Any other discussion or questions
about the the regulation change?
>> Yeah. Jim Ellis. I I do have a concern, and this has come up before, and I I thought it was addressed.
It doesn't appear to be.
In part b
refers to the net floor area of the single family dwelling.
I think we're talking about the primary dwelling.
Right. Because if
>> we're talking about taking a 2,000 square foot house
and carving out
an apartment out of that existing
2,000 square feet,
you're
talking about six sixty square feet or thereabouts.
Yep, I think that's okay.
Okay.
>> Number or what letter are you talking about? This is section b right here. It says net floor area of the apartment will be no larger than a thousand square feet and shall be no larger than 33%
of the net floor area of the single family dwelling. Okay. Is that 33% of the entire
>> of the combined,
or is it 30 okay.
Yeah. Is it is it of the combined, or is it of
what is left of that house? If you took the 2,000 square foot, you took 600
square feet out, it's 1,400.
Yep.
>> So then you go and get 33%
of the 1,400. I'm not sure that that is what was intended.
I think pretty small units.
>> Well, so let's
say you had a 2,000 square foot house. Yep.
You made an accessory apartment
that was six sixty six square feet. Okay.
>> That's onethree. But we're not differentiating between whether that six sixty square feet is
new construction
or
retrofitting the original home. Right. If somebody
>> and
I figured we would allow that latitude to try and get
more accessory apartments. But if somebody wanted to split a 2,000 square foot house
into a six
sixty six foot
accessory apartment and a thirteen thirty
four foot
primary dwelling,
I was okay with that.
That's 50 percent, though.
>> Well, 50% of what you're left with, that 50%
of the sorry. And that's what Jim's I think that's Jim's question. That's that is Jim's question.
>> I had that situation
when we built our house. We put an accessory apartment on it before you had the regulations here.
And our main house is about 2,400
square feet and a few odd feet above that. We were told that
we could build the apartment
33%
of the size of our house, so we could go up to almost 800 square feet for the apartment. We still had to have 2,400 square feet in our house.
So we have a total of like 3,200
between the two.
We couldn't take it out of our house. We had to add on to it.
>> And that sounds like it would meet this regulation, I mean, 2400 is a pretty big house. And then you're adding Yeah. 800 to that. You know? Now you're over 3,000 square feet.
Yeah.
You know, I'm not sure that the commission is looking to do that. From a practical standpoint, a lot of accessory apartments get built over garages.
And to some extent, that dictates the size, although
I'm not sure
that the regulations need to accommodate
>> I was as well. I
was trying to
keep it sort of simple.
I recognize that there were two different
ways you can interpret that.
My thought was that I looked at it both ways. And if a guy wants to split his house up
to
take the 2,000 square foot and he comes to us with a plan that says, my plan is to
make it,
let's say for ease of number 600 square feet and 1,400 square feet,
I'm okay with that plan.
You can build a case that it doesn't work,
but
a 600
square foot place and a 1,400 square foot place, those are
reasonable places in my mind. Wasn't that we
were making it a fiftyfifty duplex.
You know, it isn't
we're still maintaining the accessory apartment,
and I wanted to give the homeowner as much latitude as he can.
So, I want to get accessory apartments.
I don't want to make it harder.
>> Jed, if I'm right. This is making it easier. Go ahead, John. So yeah, no, I think, I mean,
doesn't necessarily, I mean, obviously there is some interpretation question
and that ultimately falls to the zoning officer. And I think as long as he can interpret it fairly and consistently, I think that's totally reasonable.
The number of the town of Brown Zoning Officer, and we have a regulation like this, it would basically take it as what is the starting condition of the single family residence?
And if the starting condition is
1,800 square feet,
you get up to 33% of that. And so that can be an,
you know, within the existing structure, as Jed said, it can, you can take a third of that 600 of that 1,800,
turn it into an accessory apartment, or you can build up to an additional 600
square feet in a cottage or whatever. But your starting number is 1,800.
Your accessory apartment can be no bigger than 600,
whether it's inside or outside, it's still,
you know, the calculation is based on a third of the pre existing
>> single family condition. And that's the way that I interpret it also, not
the other way. I'm interpreting it as
under, 33%
of the 2,000 square feet.
Of the original dwelling, right? Original dwelling.
Okay. Can't be over, that's what, how, how I interpret it.
And
I'm glad that Jim brought that up, because it seems like that is a I guess
>> from a practical standpoint, I mean, people build an additional accessory apartment, they may be adding on to their home at the same time.
Right.
So I
guess this regulation,
the language would accommodate that as well. I'm just trying to think it through. It would.
>> Yep. A guy with a 2,000 square foot home
could add on
a 600
square foot accessory apartment.
>> Right. But he couldn't build a 600 square foot in that 2,000 square feet. No, but I mean, in theory, someone
>> could build an addition that's not an accessory apartment to go from 2,000 to 3,000 square feet of their principal dwelling. And then the next month turn around and want to
build an accessory apartment now that they've got more principal square footage
and go up to a thousand. But that's why you have the hard cap of a thousand. So if someone can't build an addition to give themselves 6,000 square feet and then do,
you know, 30% of that, like, so, you know, it's
both and, you know, it's 33% and a hard cap with a thousand. And I think that meets
the intent.
>> So I'm okay with the words,
is there written there? Does somebody
want to make a proposal to modify them in any way?
>> Jed, I think I
kind of read
it or
think that it would be a good idea to do it the way that you're explaining it. So there is some more flexibility.
And,
you know, we never know. Every case is different, but I I don't see
too many people coming forward
with very large houses
looking to make what would then be a
sizable accessory apartment
more than what we're talking about now with the possibly more anyway with a thousand square feet.
>> And and, yeah, I don't have any problem with interpret it the way you or interpreting the way you are.
I'm just saying that I'm interpreting differently than you Well,
>> and we would have a discussion when somebody, you know, I can't envision all the different things, but what I do want to do is give the commission flexibility
to help expand the number of affordable units,
whether they count or not. We
need more affordable housing, and I think this is a good way to get some of that.
And if a guy comes in and wants to reduce the square footage of his primary thing to make it, I'm okay with that.
If we find that somewhere along the way it doesn't work, we'll change it.
>> Thank you. I'm comfortable
enforcing
that. Just wanted to be clear, and it is. Thank you.
>> Just
to be clear, this is Leanne. We're going to leave it that it can either be carved out of an existing house of x number of square feet,
or
it can be
in addition to
it it can be another
Yep.
>> Another ex you know what I mean? I hope like, maybe not, but another figure of x number of square feet for the accessory apartment that's not necessarily
carved out of the original
residence.
>> Yep.
And there could even be a case where somebody wants to add on
300 square feet and take 300 from the existing place to make a sick whatever the guy wants to do. If he wants to come in and tell us and it makes sense,
we have the latitude to approve it, and I am happy with that.
Interesting.
Okay.
Any other discussion on the accessory apartments?
>> Are we going to go over the architecture
and floor plan?
>> We can. We
can do that
now maybe.
You still see the signs
thing?
No. No. Okay. I stopped sharing, and it's on my screen.
We're going to do that.
So,
here is
So in
the proposed
accessory dwelling unit
regulation,
it talks about floor plans.
Right.
I recent
>> think
it doesn't say
you you know, it just says,
etcetera.
But I would think that the floor plan would include everything
that's
on the floor or every
you see what I mean? It says-
Okay, yep. Like, like, you know, it does, etcetera.
I
would assume that it should have everything that's gonna be on,
or on the building,
you know, not pictures and
that, but
>> On the building, I don't disagree with that. You know, if you put a propane tank out there, it should be on there. If you got,
an external heat pump, it should be listed on there.
What I did not want to get into
with the floor plan was we
sometimes talked about how much insulation is going to be in the walls and
that sort of thing. And I thought that needed to be on building plans or architectural plans, but wasn't really what we were looking at. Those were things that the building official
should be making sure are up to code. That wasn't anything that I was particularly
interested in hearing about.
I assume that it's going to be built to code.
But if there's something that's going to stick out
external to the house,
that should be on there.
There something else that you'd specifically like included there instead of the etc?
>> No. I I know, that's why I brought it up. I Yeah. You know, maybe Okay. No.
You know, external
if they're gonna be using gas as fuel,
if there's they're gonna be tanks.
>> Yep.
I think
we have the right to ask for that. I just didn't want us to get into the weeds of I know. I know. Building codes.
Okay.
Any other questions on what we're listing as a floor plan here?
And again, I think
the definition that we have for floor plan
is what in the previous
draft of the regulations
was listed as an architectural
plan.
I just crossed off architectural and put floor plan there, and then I added an architectural
plan definition
that Mark Grants provided.
And I thought that looked reasonable, too.
But at this point, we're
talking about the accessory dwelling unit
regulation.
Any more changes
or discussion on that?
Hearing none, I make a motion to amend the changes
to specify
forty years instead of ten years on that Section 4.11.2
where it was listed as ten years inconsistent with the earlier.
Second that. Thanks,
>> Anne. Any further discussion on that?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote. Anne?
Aye.
Scott? Aye.
LeeAnne?
Aye.
>> Steve?
And I vote aye as well. The motion to amend the regulation
passes five-zero-zero.
And now the
vote on the regulation
as
proposed and amended.
Anne?
Aye.
Scott? Aye.
Leigh Ann?
Aye.
>> Steve?
Aye. And I vote aye as well. The motion passes five-zero-zero.
Okay.
I think we're
we're down to
lighting.
Signs.
Okay, so the current regulation would limit us
to a height of 35 feet and
no greater than
12 lumens per square foot.
The modification
wants to have a lighting study, which would be done regardless.
Even with these restrictions in place, a lighting study would have to be conducted. But a lighting study shall
be required to determine the maximum recommended lighting fixture height
and maximum lumens per square foot based on the type of intensity of sport or use in the size of area illuminated.
I will make a motion to approve the modification
to the
site
and parking lot lighting regulation?
Second.
>> Thank you, Steve.
Any discussion
on that?
And I know at the last time we were talking about specifying
a maximum lumens per square foot based on
the
I forget the name the sport
lighting
recommendation
thing.
Eric, do recall what that was or John?
I do not. Okay. I can go back and
look at the last discussion.
I
think we saw
what
the recommendations were in there, it was significantly
greater than 12 lumens.
Like 30 or 35?
>> Yeah. Think it was 30 for the pickleball and
maybe something a little less than that for the soccer field or something, but
in that. Now,
one of the things that, you know,
I guess so we've
got an upper bounds
on the
illumination.
The
regulation is specified here does not have an upper bound on
height
except
upper bounded by checkbook
because the higher the poles go, the more expensive
it is. And
a
possible change would be we could limit it to 60 foot. I think the initial
research that Eric did had
suggested it might be about
60 feet.
Or the other thought I had was we could make it no higher than the treetops,
so you didn't have these things sticking out like the
cell phone towers
high above the treetops there.
But I'm looking for some thought
from the Commission on do we want to put an upper bound on that
or
do we want to just
the
only place I see this
lighting thing being
coming into play, well, guess it could go with the
ball fields over there at some point, but
certainly for right now, you know, we're only talking about
the soccer field.
Right.
Do we want to include something like
not to exceed 60 feet?
>> Well, I guess it is like what
is necessary
to do a good job
providing lighting
until we know
how tall you need to have them with how much light and what produces so much light. It's hard to say a
maximum height. I think we should go with what worked
instead of just
arbitrarily coming up with a height.
>> Yep. Yep.
Right. The, the trees over there are, a
little over 70 feet tall, the tallest trees. Yep.
So the, the, so the poles, if they're 60 feet,
would be less.
So you wouldn't see them if you Yeah. Look towards the trees. It's, they'll be inside the tree line in there.
That's obviously not a permanent condition.
>> No, but there's
not a lot of variation that I saw looking at the tree heights over there.
Scott tried to point out to me an oak tree that
he measured at about 72 foot high. And I went over there trying to find an oak tree that stuck out like a sore thumb higher than the rest of them. And
there wasn't a significant amount of variation with any of the trees out there.
>> There wasn't, but that was the biggest
one there. And
>> I think that
the other thing to consider with what Ann was just talking about,
I think the important thing is to
stay within the requirements
for
not intruding on adjacent properties.
And so
it's going to be a trade off.
The better we do on eliminating the shine on the neighbor's property
is going to be a function of how high we make the pole.
And I'd be willing to have the pole go a little bit higher
to protect the neighbor's
property from
being
goofed up.
Now, the other thing it talks about in here,
and I don't think that we're changing it at all,
is the plan that needs to come to us
for a special permit needs to talk about how late
the lights would be on before they are turned down to their normal
security setting.
If
the neighbor had showed up tonight, I was going to ask her how
late she thought
it would be appropriate to have the lights on to support play. But she's not here, so
we'll just recognize
that any special permit that comes to us has to address
Has to address lights would be on. And that gives the neighbors an opportunity
to provide comment and input on that. So we're
not letting
the town out of any of those requirements to specify
how late the the lights will be on and that sort of thing.
>> Right. That would be the con some of the conditions.
Yep.
>> Right. But adding the 60
60 feet,
height
would probably be a good idea, Jed.
It wouldn't be a good idea if if,
the
>> the we determined that it had to be Had to be sixty five. Yeah. Yeah.
Then
we
>> but, again, if if you know? But Eric is saying that, you know, he said, you know, the upper, you know, 57
or, as I remember,
up to 60 or 55 to 60, I think he might have said.
>> Eric, you got any thoughts on,
living with the 60 foot height restriction?
Or,
>> So
not sure I'm supposed to be talking at this point, but if I was talking, I would say I don't have a problem with a 60 foot height restriction.
>> K? Not sure we're supposed to be listening
at this point,
but if we were
>> Couldn't we just leave it the way it is? Because it's requiring a special permit with a lighting study that specifies the height that they want.
>> It is. But there's you know, they could come in with the the words the way it is. What if they came in with a 100 foot?
Right. But we don't have to approve that. Like, what would your grounds for disapproval be?
Well, aesthetically,
we don't
>> like it. You could go that way. Yep. You
could do that.
And so
>> I just think leaving it the way we've got it worded gives us that flexibility.
>> Okay.
So
any other comments?
Anybody else got thoughts? No.
I will make
a motion to amend
the proposed changes
to put an upper limit on the illumination
based on
the appropriate
athletic field lighting standard.
And I'll get the right name for that.
And I will recognize
so,
boom, that's the end of the modification.
As a side note to that,
I will recognize that that standard does not include pickleball courts.
And I would think that
the Commission,
if somebody came in with a plan to light the pickleball courts,
and they said there was not a standard for that in the athletic field illumination
guidelines.
But they found
a similar
limit,
which we know
the number is 30.
For the pickleball court guidelines,
we would say that just like when we talk about parking,
we've got a bunch of examples for requirements.
And if the thing that you're doing isn't quite in there, you find one that fits close,
and we could go with that.
There's not going be a perfect answer. Or I could put the pickleball guidelines
in there. But
I think
that if we specify
the athletic field illumination
guidelines,
that's good enough.
Can work with that. Yeah.
So anyhow, that's my discussion
on the proposed amendment.
Any other discussion on that?
Okay, I'll call for a vote on the amendment.
Anne?
Aye.
Scott?
Aye. Leigh Ann?
Aye.
>> Steve?
And I vote aye as well. So the amendment to the proposed regulation passes
five-zero-zero.
And now we'll vote on the
section modification.
Anne?
Aye.
Scott?
>> Leigh Ann?
Aye.
Steve?
And I vote aye as well. That motion passes five-zero-zero.
Last up is definitions.
And we've got
one, two, three,
four,
five,
six
definitions
here.
I will make a motion to approve
the change to the definition section.
I'll second that. Okay. Thanks, Scott.
Any discussion on the definitions?
I would like to make one modification
to this proposed change,
and that is to eliminate from the
definition section the definition of a billboard.
When we changed section 15, we changed the definition of a billboard in that,
and it was no longer consistent with what's in section 24.
The standard we have
chosen
for where to put definitions is that if a definition exists only in one chapter,
the definition will be in that chapter. If the definition is used in more than one chapter or section,
then it should reside in
Section 24.
The only place we talk about billboards is in Section 15 on the signs.
And so I don't think it's appropriate
to be in two different places
and have two different definitions.
I
would make the amendment to eliminate
the
definition of billboard from Section 24.
Any other discussion
on
the definitions?
>> Are we gonna change the lot frontage thing?
Frontage?
Are we gonna leave it because it's adjacent?
>> Good point, Scott. And
So I
will change my proposed
modification to delete the billboard
definition
and add the words
as in a corner lot
after adjacent to each other.
Okay.
>> And it's specific. Right? Yep. Thank you, Scott.
Any other comments on the definitions?
Okay.
Hearing none, I
will call for a vote on the
amendment to the proposed changes.
Anne?
Did I?
Oh, am I muted?
>> Nope. I got you this time. Yep. Didn't hear you before. Scott?
Aye. Leanne?
Aye.
>> Steve?
Aye. And I vote aye as well. That
motion passes five-zero-zero.
And now to
vote on the modified
changes to the definitions
as amended.
Anne?
Aye.
Scott?
Aye. Leigh Ann?
Aye.
Steve?
>> Aye. And I vote aye as well. That motion passes five-zero-zero.
And by
not discussing
Section 4.21
because the town
has
pulled their request for that,
I think we are done.
Thank you.
Those have been a long time coming.
Next up on the old business is the application of the town of Andover improvements to the public safety complex.
Eric,
I'll let you take that one.
>> Okay.
Thank you, Commission.
Can
I share my screen right now? No, I can't.
So, you make it so that I can share my screen, please?
Okay. While Marina is hopefully working on that, I will just talk you through.
The town is asking
for a site plan modification
to
allow the town to put in two additional
1,000
gallon propane tanks
on a pad
adjacent
to two existing 1,000 gallon propane tanks
located
behind the fire safety complex
and next to
kinda kiddie corner to the town office building
and community center.
Yep. There we go.
So let me see whether I got the right one here.
Okay, you should be looking at a basic site plan
and I just cannedrew the location in of the proposed tank.
I also submitted the engineering drawings for that, but I did not put the engineering drawings and the proposed site map on the same location.
So,
this
has been approved by the Inland Wetlands Commission,
it has been approved by Eastern Highlands Health District,
and it has been signed off on by the Fire Marshal,
so which should be prerequisites
to your approving it.
So that's basically it. I mean, the ultimate goal of this is to
allow two things. It allows us to
transition to a propane
backup generator
that will cover
the fire safety complex,
the town hall,
the community center.
That means one generator will be able to run what will be the
emergency shelter,
the town emergency operations center, as well as the fire department.
And we'll reuse the old
diesel generator at public works because although this generator is 30 years old, the one at public works is 56 years old.
So it will still be
a positive change for them. So in a nutshell, that is what we're doing.
Does the commission have any questions?
>> Okay. I don't hear any there, Eric.
Jim,
have you I know you were working on the checklist for this, and Eric
listed three
things that were crucial to
its approval.
What is your take on the application?
>> Yeah, walked through the checklist
and
everything seems to be in order.
The wetland permit is posted.
The
Eastern Highlands
district approval is posted,
as is the fire marshal's
comment.
I have no issues with the application.
>> Okay.
So there are essentially two ways that we could go
with this as a commission. If we considered it a minor change like we did
with the ad in the gazebo over at
I think it was Network
or something, is that the name of the building?
Route 6.
We told
we authorized the zoning agent Jim to go handle that change.
The other
thing we can do is we can
vote on it as a commission.
And I think that
in my sense,
the
change is relatively minor.
If it's got
wetlands approval and the fire marshal approval, I'm not sure what the sanitarian did, but I was interested in those two approvals.
I think it might be just quicker and easier if we voted on it as the Commission.
And with that in mind,
I will make a motion to approve
the application
for the addition of the propane tanks behind the firehouse.
I'll second that, Jeff. Okay. Thanks, Scott.
>> Any discussion
on that at all by
anybody present?
Hearing none, I will call for a vote. Anne?
Aye.
Scott? Aye.
Leigh Ann?
Aye.
>> Steve?
Aye. And I vote aye as well. The motion passes five-zero-zero.
Next up on the agenda is the update of the plan of conservation and development.
And John,
I think your plan was to
show us the survey that you were working on?
>> Yeah, if it's possible. And Marina, could I share screen also?
So we sort of went through last month
the
questions that were
let me share this
one there.
So does this look like a SurveyMonkey
dashboard?
Yes. Okay. So
we went on through some of the long range planning
study
questions from last time, as well as
looking at some of the
general priorities when it comes to
development issues, economic development, housing development, as well as conservation,
municipal
services, municipal resources.
So based on that
conversation and that history,
as well as some other plan of conservation and development surveys I've done, I basically put together a draft,
which I'm gonna run through briefly.
But what I would propose to do is this survey is actually live right now. Nobody has formally responded to it because nobody knows the address, but
it is live and people can review it at their leisure. So I'll run through it and then we'll share the link and encourage people to sort of take a look before we kind of start advertising it to the public.
>> Before
you start there, John, one of the things that surprised me on the last survey that we did, which was on the POCD actions,
once you submit the survey,
I was not able to get back to the survey again. So if I wanted to go back and see what the questions were and that sort of thing, I couldn't get there. Yeah, you have to go a library
or something like that. Yeah. Yeah.
>> So get one shot at Be careful. Don't submit it until you're done with it thinking you'll go back and what else should we be talking about?
Once you submit it, you're done.
>> So, I mean, we can reset this or move it to a different address or whatever if we need to do that sort of thing.
So a brief introduction
here and hopefully people are able to see, again, noting that this is a ten year plan,
encouraging people's thoughtful responses and adding my email if anyone has questions.
Simple question, live or work in Andover with, you know, opportunities for
both employees in town, people who live in town or
both,
as well as people who are retired or basically
have a vacation home, try to cover, you know, as many of those
ownership or work bases as possible.
Then we went to a couple of, and so this again, being surveyed, you know, there's, you could do multiple choice. You could do check all of the above.
I chose to use Akira, a couple of ranking things
to essentially force choices, because obviously you could say, which of these things are important?
You know, in many cases, all of them are important, but in order to help set priorities, we wanted to force some rankings.
So looking at economic development priorities, we set up seven choices.
And basically what this will do is it allows people to drag
choices up or down,
one through seven, one being the most important
and seven being the least.
No major, like, and again, this is economic development, so we are okay. No major development.
>> You demonstrate that, John? Because it took me
a little time to figure out how
that was working there.
>> Yeah, let me go to preview.
So, yeah, okay. So this would be,
>> let's say, can you see this right here, the choices? Yeah. Just like you want to take the second one and make it the first priority. Basically,
>> could either click the up arrow
over here and it would go to the top. Or if you want to say, let's take more restaurants along six,
you can click it and just drag it up to the top.
And so this is, it's dynamic. You can reorder these things however you want. And then you'll note the numbers are changing on the right, on the left rather. So visitor based businesses, so we want to move that to number two, then everything else moves below it. So there's a couple of ways of reorganizing,
of reordering.
And so the choices here, more restaurants along 6,
visitor based businesses to leverage Hopper Trail, etcetera.
No major changes.
More service, professional medical offices along 6,
focus on growing existing small businesses,
more small businesses and home based businesses throughout town, not just six,
and then more retail along Route 6,
>> mainly grocery, pharmacy, convenience. And what I'd like the commission to do is
think about,
is there something else that should be on that list that
we haven't thought of
so that we can make sure that we're getting the right kind of inputs?
And
I'm not saying there is, but
the goal of going through this tonight is so that you guys can all think about this and we provide some
input to John next time we get together.
>> Or
in the interim. Certainly, it's
very easy to edit these things,
to change words
or to add questions. So I'll go through, if you have some immediate thoughts, and again, please don't
feel on the spot to
judge these things. I just wanna run through and then you can review this more at your leisure.
Then we get into a couple of questions about housing.
If you think more housing options are needed in Andover, for whom are they most needed? And this would be
select all, this is not a ranking.
So the answer could very well be all of the above, seniors and downsizers,
young professionals, teachers, young families,
second homes or vacation homes.
And then again, one of the options is,
I don't think we need more housing options. So again, try to cover the
range. But again, and this will,
it's not a ranking, so it could be sort of an all of the above
option.
And then aside from who or for whom the housing is for, what type,
and this is a suggestion that Jed added earlier today,
which is, you know, single family. And again, this could be an all of the above, single family residences, single family with accessory,
two family or duplex, three or four family,
townhouse or multifamily, and then other.
How about
How about yurts? We should allow yurts,
definitely.
>> You you say that you you have you know, you don't appreciate how easy it is to add yurts to these things. You wanna add yurts, we can add yurts.
Think it will move there.
>> All right. And then we go into community
resilience and sustainability, and this is another ranking, ranking the areas of focus or investment from the town.
So we include alternative energy infrastructure,
which would be solar or EV charging stations,
upgraded power data infrastructure,
making sure Andover's road network is friendlier to pedestrians and bicycles,
community gardens and expanding local agriculture,
discouraging new construction and public investment in flood prone or environmentally sensitive areas, or investing in creating access and infrastructure to recreational resources.
So this is sort of thinking about
sustainability,
so thinking about where
Andover should be putting its sort of governmental focus on
some of these elements.
And there could very well be more of these.
I would caution,
however, with rankings,
if you get more than six or seven things, it gets very difficult to sort of keep all those things in your head to properly rank them.
And it kind of loses some of its value.
>> John, can I ask a quick
question?
When,
so say we get 100 people,
you're just basically
summing up for each category what
its respective rank is and coming up with the average numerical order. Is that Exactly.
>> So in this case, you know, one being the top priority, but the lowest
average number would be the collective top priority.
Understood. Thank you.
>> So we ask a similar question about open space and natural resource priorities.
Well, like again, trying to force a choice because there are limited funds and limited resources for the town to invest in certain natural resources. So
weighing these things against each other is important.
So again, focusing efforts on Andover Lake,
water quality and public access,
trails,
stewardship and management of existing open space, as opposed to investing in new purchase.
Active recreation facilities, such as playgrounds, athletic fields.
More passive open space, forests and habitat.
And then the
option that we have sufficient
open space resources as it stands.
>> Question, how does that fit in if you're ranking them
and you say we have,
oh, okay, nevermind. I see,
yeah,
There are enough other things in that category. Makes sense. Nevermind.
>> And
then, so these long range planning topics, again, these were taken from the survey that was done a few years ago.
And again, sort of judging people's agreement with them, which is more or less how it was asked
in the long range planning topics. Although I think in a lot of those, it was basically a binary,
you know, do you support this? Do you not support this? So I wanted to add a little bit more
range of response.
So
focusing efforts on developing a town center. And so this is a five
category
from strongly agree to strongly disagree
to sort of get some nuanced opinion on this. Are we establishing a main street
to actively market
available and undeveloped commercial land on Route 6,
improvements to be made to Route 316
for bike and ped,
and then focusing less on acquiring open space and more on maintenance and
stewardship of current lands. So a lot of these, again, were taken more or less verbatim from
the Oblong planning study, but we wanna kinda
get people's temperature on this again. Because, you know, and long range planning study, obviously recent, but it was pre COVID and a lot of things have changed about how we see
our relationship to our community.
Then we go to
the following services,
which
I had a discussion about today with
a colleague and it's,
I decided not to do which of these are important services for the town to provide, because clearly the would
be all of the above, you know, roads are important, schools are important, course, open space is important, but I'm
curious to get a sense of
how people see
what the town does for them being
the most important. What is the, you know, if Again,
this is the classic sort of guns or butter. You know, we have a limited budget, what we should be focusing our money on.
So included the public schools, senior services,
general government services, parks and rec, public works, including road maintenance and then transportation, which I think, you know, I could have missed some major category of government service, but I think this covers most of it. And a lot of these categories were taken from the long range planning
study.
And this was the one I'm actually most curious about seeing the results of.
And then we added a couple of
sort of forward looking questions about Andover's future, you know, not only
as a community, but in, you know, in the world as it stands. So we asked about climate change
and again, a five
level
questionnaire of very concerned to not concerned at all,
changing demographics in the aging world population,
aging infrastructure,
loss of sense of place or character,
which again is sort of
a catchall for a number of different things, but it's something that we hear a lot in communities like Andover.
Overdevelopment or loss of natural resources,
pandemic
and public health,
slow economic growth,
changing housing patterns and affordability.
So we kind of wanna get a sense of where people stand on some of these forward looking ideas, as well as adding a comment option.
And then we asked a couple of open ended questions,
which again, looking at the next ten years for the plan.
What's a hope and what's a concern? So open ended responses there.
And then we asked a couple of basic
communications questions.
What's the best way to get information to people? And we're not asking for emails, but rather just
how do they get information and what's the best way to get information out there?
Emails, newspaper, card copy questionnaires, website, direct mail, that sort of thing.
And then a couple of demographic questions,
age,
rent or own a property, and then household income,
as well as final
hopes or concerns,
about the, you know, open ended response.
So
you can see on the right, SurveyMonkey
has these tools. There are no technical problems that they found in the survey in terms of logic, which is good.
It is a little long, you know, 16 questions, estimating a completion rate of 70%. If we made it shorter,
we could get a higher completion rate, but that's not terrible.
And about a ten or eleven minute
timeframe.
So,
you know, if you can do a survey in about ten minutes, I think, you know, we could get some decent
response and then it you know, so the two the two next things that I would like to
get over the next month or so is, again, more robust response from you guys. Obviously, you're just seeing this for the first time.
And I'll I'll I'll share the link.
And then following that, what's the best way once we've got sort of final wording,
what's the best way to start spreading the word and getting this out there? And I think, you know, multiple
venues and multiple
notifications is the way to go. But I'll stop talking and see if anyone has questions or comments at this point.
>> John, in terms of getting the word out there,
we would definitely use the town's social media. We
would use our push notification
system.
We would put it in the newspaper,
and we would probably
commit to sending a flyer to every household,
with the the link information.
>> Yeah. And we can we can embed a QR code also if you wanted to do that.
>> Yeah, now the other question that I would have is that
a certain fraction, if you're trying to get a fair
degree of response from seniors,
you probably have a significant fraction of them that don't have
internet access or enough savvy to use a SurveyMonkey
platform.
Is there an alternative
method
having them do the survey?
>> Yes. So we do printed,
we can do a more user friendly printed version
that they can return. And then on the back end of SurveyMonkey,
I can physically enter
dozens or hundreds of hard copy responses,
you know, just by filling them out online.
>> So we could do something like
say, in
a newspaper article,
if you want a hard copy to send back in, you'll call or email
well, call this number at town hall, and we'll send you out a copy as opposed to just send, using the postage
to send it out to everybody.
>> Yeah, or we could leave a
stack at the library, leave a stack at town hall, leave a stack at, you know,
post office, whatever. Yep, okay.
>> But I think what we wanna do is we wanna request people
to do it online,
to
make our lives easier. And then only if they're unwilling to do it online or incapable of doing it online,
do we offer the secondary member or secondary method.
John, I think it's great overall. I think that it's an interesting
I haven't seen
that elaborate one in SurveyMonkey.
So it's good to see the possibilities.
>> And, you know, then there's also, you know, on back end, there there'd be also opportunities for
crosstabbing these things, you know, assuming we get, I'll
think very positively, and let's say we'll get 10%,
15% of the town. So we get, you know, four or 500
that, you know, we can do crosstabs. So, you know, people that own their house believe that, you know,
roads are most important or people that rent believe the schools are most important or people over the age of 65 believe that senior services are most important. And we can kind of do some of those crosstabs as well.
>> Yeah, when I went through it, John, my first comment was it wasn't long enough.
But your point about getting people actually take
ten minutes of their time to fill out a survey is
very good. And I
couldn't come up with a bunch of things other I thought for the 16 questions you had there, it sort of covered everything. So
the homework for the commission is to
poke holes at it next meeting and see what else we need to do. But I think it's an excellent starting point, John.
>> Yeah, thank you. So yeah, Jed, I will, the link that I sent you and Eric today is the same. So if you want to
forward that link out to the commission,
we can have people
review.
>> Okay. So
I didn't know that I got a link from you today. I thought it was know, I got the one a day or two ago that I Yeah. Yeah. I'm sorry. Right. Okay. That's the one. Okay. Yeah. I'll send that out to
everybody here. So
thanks, John. Thank you.
Thank you.
>> That's
it for old business. We're going to move on to item seven, approval of the minutes from the regular meeting on November 21.
Anybody have any comments on the meeting minutes?
And I had only one on page two of three
under new business section seven
license day. The A is missing from care.
And that was the only change that I have for that, Marina.
Anybody else have any comments on the minutes?
Hearing none, I'll call
for a vote on the minutes as amended by the one typo.
Anne?
Aye.
Scott? Aye.
Leanne?
Leanne, you might be on mute.
Going to go on to Steve at this point?
Aye.
And I vote aye as well, Leanne?
I'll I'll count that as an abstention.
So the motion passes
four zero one with Leanne abstaining.
>> He put up her hand up. Oh, she did? Yeah.
I can't even see her. She normally
>> Look on her picture.
You got a picture, Leanne? No. No. No. But she put a hand up where Oh, okay. I gotcha.
>> But then
we'll take that as an I then. It's an I. So, yeah,
the minutes are approved five-zero-zero.
Thank you, Scott.
Next up on the agenda
is the administrative report. Jim?
>> Yes.
Gravel pit has been referred to
Mark France, delegated
the matter to
attorney Alan Curto,
who has been in contact with me, said he's working on
year end issues, and we'll get to it
hopefully very soon.
Other than that, I have
nothing to add.
Okay.
Number of enforcement
issues, 117 Long Hill Road,
92 Merritt Valley Road,
and
225 Route 6, various debris.
I have
some letters letters have gone out and trying to work with owners on that. Do have a commitment from a gentleman in Merritt Valley.
480 Lake Road, I did notify the owner of
Ben Franklin, concerned about site plan issues.
And
let me go back and revisit. He's gonna take a look at his lighting and
hopefully get his camper off that property.
I have that calendar for thirty days thirty days out.
357 Lake Road, a situation with a
garage built without a permit
and
owner living in the house without a CFO. And
that has
been referred to the town attorney, not not not
attorney branch, but
Dennis O'Brien because it involves the building inspector who who does not currently cover
is not covered under Mark Brantz's
purview.
Route 6.
The owner is, that's Steve Barnett property. A lot of debris,
junk.
He's been working on it
steadily.
Looks a lot better, thoughtfully in compliance.
He did appeal his citation,
and
a hearing will be set up. We we do have a hearing officer.
And, again,
attorney O'Brien is working with that hearing officer to
address that. This would be the first blight citation
complaint that was appealed.
>> Has he done anything, Jim, on the zoning
change that he was
asking about?
Dennis?
Burnett?
>> No. He has not. Okay. He's
been made aware of the situation, and
I will
try and
I mean, more specifically, what that is is the
property
he had gone to the Planning and Zoning Commission a number of years ago
and effectively had had the zone change, but never filed a map.
So
there is no map as far as I know, and he's gonna have to come up with one. So,
>> Jim, not to
interrupt you, but what is he appealing?
>> It's a good question, Scott. It was he's appealing
the just
the notification. The he's appealing the citation
that he
is cleaning it up. It doesn't make any sense to me, quite honestly. We'll
see how that plays out.
I understand your question, and I I can appreciate.
He doesn't really have a a real solid appeal, in my opinion.
>> Well, the only thing
he could appeal is that he does not have a blight
condition.
>> Or he can appeal yes. And he can appeal the the apparently, he can appeal the amount of of the fine,
but the days of the fine.
That's about it.
Yeah. He he can say that
that his property is not in in in
violation,
and
I don't see him going anywhere with that.
There's substantial documentation
in form of pictures
over time.
That's all I have.
>> Jim, one of the things that would be helpful
is to have a
listing,
if you will, that gets tacked onto the agenda of all the different things you're working.
Because when you talk about
whatever on Merritt Valley Road, it took me a while to remember. We're talking about the couple of trucks that are parked out in front of the property, I think, and trying to get those eliminated.
>> Well, what happened was those trucks were removed,
but the
contents of the truck were placed on the front yard.
>> So But
anyhow,
the
point is it would be helpful for us to
we forget what
>> issues are. In fact, I have a matrix of light and zoning violations
that I maintain and I provide to
Eric on an occasional basis,
which I can certainly make available. I can send out
>> with the agenda. Because the other thing just
to keep in mind is
there are a few
zoning
deficiencies out there, like the church
and the temple that need to come in and get special permit and all those. And
we would forget about them if
Right. They are on my list. Yep. Okay. Very good. Thank you.
Far as the inland wetlands and water course liaison, I have nothing to report to the commission on that.
The last thing we talked about was the
propane tanks and we approved
that
application there.
Item nine on the agenda is Commission discussion.
Anybody have anything
they would like to discuss?
Okay.
Hearing that, item 10 is miscellaneous.
And that probably,
if
anybody has anything under miscellaneous,
now is a good time to talk about that.
>> I have something, Jed, if people Go ahead, John, yep. Because this will be before I see you all next time.
If people are fans of the TV show Jeopardy!
I
just wanted to let people know I will be back on Jeopardy! As
part of the Second Chance Tournament on January 11 is the air date. That's a Thursday night.
So any trivia fans out there can see me on TV.
>> Good luck, John. Yeah. Good luck. Good luck. And, well
That's cool. You're the first guy I ever knew that made it to Jeopardy.
>> Wow. I just wanna say now that I knew you before you became famous.
We have proof. This meeting is recorded.
>> I
guess the other thing under miscellaneous,
again, I'd like to
welcome Anne Marie to the Commission.
And
sometimes we take a little time during the meeting to talk about what the expectations are and that sort of thing. And this meeting is running a little long, so we won't do that tonight.
Maybe after the start of the new year, we'll set up a meeting with
Jim and I and
kind of go through
what to do to get you up to speed the best we can and answer questions that you might have and that sort of thing. So
welcome, and we'll figure out how we can help
get you into
the commission as well.
And you're on mute if you were trying to say something.
Nope, okay.
Enough for miscellaneous.
Moving on to public comments.
Nobody from the public is here.
Date of the next regular scheduled meeting is January
16.
I think I checked that on my calendar and that was
correct with the Tuesday. Yep.
And
Jim, as I recall, you mentioned you will not be available for the next meeting. Is that That's correct. Okay.
I thought about trying to move it, thought about trying to change it,
thought about
canceling it.
And I came to the conclusion that we'll do it. And
the thing that we should be focused on for the next meeting, because I'm not aware of any applications coming our way for that one, will be to
spend the time discussing the
survey that we went through tonight. So we'll
do that. And if that doesn't take very long, we'll start the new year off with a short meeting.
But Jed
>> Jed, can I interject one thing?
I think you can probably assume that the commission will see some eight twenty four statutory referrals
for the next
meet,
And they will likely be for the parking area
for a proposed
trail between the town of Andover and Joshua's Trust, number one, and then likely a referral
for a boundary line adjustment
between
the town and a resident for the property
that is on
off of Burnett Brook Road
and also potentially
one for a boundary line
agreement
between
the town and an abutter
directly behind the Andover Elementary School to correct a minor,
very minor deficiency
that was determined when we had it surveyed by BSC.
So
you will probably see all three of those
at your next meeting. Okay,
>> very good. And
we'll tackle them when we get them.
Anne Marie, I saw your note saying
you are back with us now. I just wanted to welcome you to the Commission. And
after the start of the year, we'll try and set up a time at your convenience to get together with Jim and I, and we'll go through,
things for you to look at.
This
is a good time for you to be joining the Commission.
We're working on the next ten year plan with the Plan of Conservation and Development. So spend some time looking through
that and
figuring out what you think we need to change to make Andover better.
That sounds great. Thank you. That's I look the forward to
going forward there.
Thanks very much. So
>> we talked about the next date,
January 16.
Jim won't be here.
The last comment before we make a motion to adjourn is that
I'd like to wish everybody,
Yohan, your continued support.
I very much appreciate that. We got a lot of stuff, a lot of business done tonight.
And
>> I wish everybody a very happy, healthy, and safe holiday season. And we will hit it again next year. So
enjoy the Thank time you. With your Yep.
And all that being said, I will make a motion to
adjourn
at 09:40.
Second.
>> Thank you. That was Leigh Ann?
Yes. Yep. Okay. Good enough.
All in favor, raise your hand.
One, two, three.
Okay.
I'm raising my hand. Okay. Yeah. Thank you, Lee Ann. Motion passes
five-zero-zero.
Happy holidays, everybody. Enjoy
the next couple of weeks. Thank you. And good night. Happy holidays. Bye. Good night, everyone. Good night. Bye.